Guide to the Council of Church Boards of Education Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Council of Church Boards of Education Records
1920-1949
RG 236
Yale University Divinity School Library
5.8
(14 boxes)
The Council of Church Boards of Education was a Protestant ecumenical organization created in 1911. The organization was made up of boards of education from several Protestant denominations. The intent of the organization was to promote the cause of religious education in institutions of higher education.
Council of Church Boards of Education in the United States of America
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Princeton Theological Seminary Library, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
On February 18, 1911, Dr. Thomas Nicholson called a meeting of secretaries from various denominational boards of education to discuss and collaborate on their common issues. This meeting led to the creation of the Council of Church Boards of Education (CCBE), which was an interdenominational organization concerned with Christian education in normal schools, colleges, and universities. The aims of the council were to promote and strengthen Christian education within institutions of higher education. It accomplished these aims by being a clearing house for information on the subject. The CCBE released several publications, including the journal Christian Education and the handbook Christian Higher Education. In addition, it conducted surveys on religious education in higher education, coordinated conferences, acted as a consultant to college campuses, and produced several radio addresses. The Council of Church Boards of education also assisted in the founding of the American Association of Colleges. In 1947 the organization changed its name to the National Protestant Council of Higher Education, and in 1950 it was absorbed into the National Churches of Christ in the USA's Commission on Higher Education.
Scope and Contents
The Council of Church Boards of Education archives cover the period 1920-1949 with the bulk of records in the mid 1930s to early 1940s when Gould Wickey was the executive secretary. The materials are divided into four series with documents arranged alphabetically by name or subject. Records are organized chronologically within the alphabetical structure. The documents represent the administrative and program actions of the CCBE. Series I contains correspondence to organizations within and outside the CCBE. Series II houses materials generated by the CCBE such as meeting minutes, news clippings, publicity information, and reports. Series III contains conference materials and information about events programmed by the CCBE and other conferences attended. Series IV contains material from organization the CCBE were in contact with such as promotion information from colleges, meeting minutes and reports.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Council of Church Boards of Education Records
III. Conferences
IV. Organizations
Religious education -- United States; Council of Church Boards of Education in the United States of America
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Boy, Girl Scouts, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Calhoun Manuscript God and the Day's Work, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campus and Church, 1939-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Campus co-visiting of National Secretaries for Students to the Campus of the University of Iowa program, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Campus Missions and Religious Emphasis Week, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carbondale, Ill, Southern Illinois Normal University, student situation, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conference of Church Workers: North Central Conference - University Committee, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Conference of Church Workers: Northeastern Conference, University committee, tentative program, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conference of Church Workers: California, program, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Conference on Religious Research, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Council of North American Student Christian Movements (CNASCM), 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Council on Religious Freedom, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence of the Director of Study of Higher Education for the Committee on Education, 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Far Eastern Student Service Fund, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Form Documents - CCBE to National Commission on University Work, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Frank D. Dorey on interracial schools or religion, 1946, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Heiges, Donald, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Institute for Propaganda Analysis, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interchurch Campus conferences bulletin, report, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Interchurch Campus conferences bulletin, report, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Intercollegian and Far Horizons, 1939-1943 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Interdenominational Student Assembly, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Interdenominational Student Work, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Japanese American Student Relocation, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Liquor Traffic pamphlets, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Westminster Foundation, Methodist Episcopal Church, Columbia University, etc.), 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Missionary Conference - Christmas, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Motion Pictures, 1934, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Association of Biblical Instructors program, announcement, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - National Association of Manufacturers, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Commission on University Work: Miscellaneous correspondence University Commission is made up of student secretaries of the Constituent Boards of the CCBE, 1931-1947 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - National Commission on University Work: History, 1932-1940 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - National Commission on University Work: Report of General Secretary, Report of Chairman to University Commission; finance statement, 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - National Commission on University Work: Form letters and Misc., 1938-1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - National Commission on University Work: Report to CCBE of Chairman and General Secretary, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - National Commission on University Work: Meetings, agenda, 1940-1943 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews pamphlet, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - National Co-operating Committee on Christian Reconstruction 156 Fifth Ave, New York City, brochure, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - National Council of Soviet Friendship pamphlets, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - National Council of Student Christian Associations, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - National Council on Religion in Education directory, 1939-1946 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - National Education Association, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - National Home Study Council - Washington, D.C. Manual, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - National Institute of Applied Religion, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - National Intercollegiate Christian Council (NICC) material, 1938-1944 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - National Patriotic Council, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - National Religion and Labor Foundation bulletins, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - National Youth Administration, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Naval Chaplaincy Training Program - Plan V-12, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Newman Club report, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Omnibus Bill, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Oxford-Edinburgh Joint Committee, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Periodicals - Denominational, 1936-1943 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Preaching Mission - National Pamphlets, handbook, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Press Clipping Bureau-clippings, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Provisional Council - Financial World's Student Christian Federation, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Publication, book review, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Race Relations - Conferences in Education, etc, minutes, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Radio - National Religious Radio broadcasts, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Religion and Welfare Recovery program, 1935-1940 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Religion in State Institutions, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Religious Census (States), 1935-1936 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Religious Drama Fellowship bulletin, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Religious Education Weeks, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Research - Thesis, Problems and Projects, 1936-1941 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Research - Thesis, Problems and Projects (cont'd), 1936-1941 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Robert Mackie (World's Student Christian Federation), 1942 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Salary Stabilization Law, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Selective Drafts - Union Seminary Student Refusals, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Service Men's Christian League handbook, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Service of Prayer and Dedication for Peace, financial statements, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Seventh-Day Adventists: Dept of Education program, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Shedd, C.P. - Book "The Church Follows Its Students" outline, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Shedd, C.P. - Book "The Church Follows Its Students" outline (cont'd), 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Social Security Act - articles, handbook, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Stewardship pamphlet (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Student Volunteer Movement, 1936-1945 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Taxes - On gifts, church property, corresp, Gift tax return forms, 1935-1946 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Toronto Student Conference - Christmas week, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - United Christian Youth Movement attendance, 19396-1943 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Culture of Organization (UNESCO) bulletins, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - United Nations West - Sept 3-9, 1946 pamphlet and letter, September 3-9, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - United Service Organization, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - University Action Committee, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - University Christian Mission handbook, manual, brochures, sports, minutes; National Preaching Mission., 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - University Christian Mission handbook, manual, brochures, sports, minutes; National Preaching Mission (cont'd), 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - University Christian Mission, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - VE (Victory in Europe) Day; article, May 8, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - War poems, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Washington Federation of Churches; record of year's work., 1936-1943 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - World Calendar Association, inc., 1946 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - World's Student Christian Federation min, pamphlets, 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - World Student Service Fund (WSSF) handbook, reports, min, 1940-1945 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - World's Sunday School Association minutes, 1938-1944 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Young Men's Christian Association: Ministerial Studies, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - YMCA and Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Youth Program and development of history of joint program, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 98)
- Council of Church Boards of Education, Series II
  - Aims and Objectives, brochures, and corresp., 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Annual Reports of the General Secretary to CCBE, 1940-1947 (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Bibliography of denominations and for student work presented at the meeting of the Commission on University Work, April 16, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - CEA (Church Educational Associates) programs and the CCBE, 1924, 1928, 1930; and committee on teacher training in colleges, 1920, 1920, 1924, 1928, 1930 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Committee on the Closer Relationships of General Interdenominational Agencies - reports and corresp. (1 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Committee on the Closer Relationships of General Interdenominational Agencies - reports and corresp.(cont'd 2 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Committee on the Closer Relationships of General Interdenominational Agencies - reports and corresp.(cont'd 3 of 3), 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Committee on Policy and Program. The report of special committee on policy and program was mailed to each secretary with April financial report and activities, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Directories of CCBE, 1935, 1940, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - A message from Henry C. Link - article, 1939-1940 (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Historical Data CCBE - When? Why? How? By Bishop Thomas Nicholson C.E. Volume 14, 1929-1942 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Information - requests for CCBE, 1941-1947 (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - Joint Sessions of the Educational Associations and the CCBE report, The Read House, Chattanooga, TN, Jan 10,1929 (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Leach Report (CCBE) for 1932-1933 by Raymond Hotchkiss Leas and Report on the Survey of Religious and Character Influences on State University and College Campuses in the Area West of the Rocky Mountains by Philip A. Parsons, Ph.D. (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Liberal Arts College Bulletin, 1930-1931 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Listings - CCBE, 1939-1941, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Members Constituent Boards - CCBE, 1941-1947 (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - National Commission on University Work of the CCBE, Sept 27, 1929 - Jan 1, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - National Commission on University Work - Minutes, 1937-1939 (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - National Commission on University Work - Minutes, 1940-1946 (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - National Commission on University Work - Minutes, 1943-1947 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - National Commission on University Work - Studies of the Relationship between General Youth work and Student work in the Denominations in the NCUW 2cc, Louisville, KY, Student work, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - National Education Planning Commission article, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Objective of Constituent Boards of CCBE (1935, 1940-41); brochures (1930, 1940), 1930-1941 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Peace Demonstrations in re. clippings, bulletins, and corresp., 1935-1936 (Box 10, Folder 123)
  - Personnel for Programs, 1935, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Philanthropy - "The Future of Educational Philanthropy", November 1944 (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Projects - CCBE Chronologically, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Publicity - CCBE, 1937, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Radio Addresses, sermons and correspondence re. promotion on radio, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Radio Directory and Use of Radio, 1938-1941 (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - References in journals to work of CBBE and National Conference of Church-Related Colleges; articles and bulletins, 1940-1943 (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Report of Union Mass Meeting CCBE, Jan 10, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Report - Mass Meeting held under the auspices of CCBE at Hotel Astor, New York City, Thursday, Jan 10, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 132)
  - Report - Union Mass Meeting CCBE Hotel Congress, Chicago 2 copies, Jan 13, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 133)
  - Scholarships - Rhodes Scholarship application and corresp., 1938 (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Stationery - CCBE, 1945-1947 (Box 11, Folder 135)
  - University Committee - History and corresp., 1928 (Box 11, Folder 136)
  - Univ. Com: Summary of the Conference of National Student Secretaries and Ann Arbor Student Ministers; reports of the Professional Activities of the University Pastor and Teacher of Religion; History of the School of Religion of the State Univ of Iowa, 1939-1942 (Box 11, Folder 137)
  - University Pastor Bulletin, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 138)
- Conferences, Series III
  - CCBE Conferences
    - Nineteenth Annual Meeting CCBE, The Willard Hotel, Washington, D.C., Jan 14, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 139)
    - Twentieth Annual Meeting CCBE, Indianapolis - official papers re. CCBE, Jan 20-21, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    - Twenty-first Annual Meeting CCBE, Cincinnati, Ohio, Jan 18-22, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 141)
    - Twenty-second Annual Meeting of the CCBE New York, February 1933 (Box 11, Folder 142)
    - Twenty-third Annual Meeting CCBE, St. Louis, MO; Triennial Conference of Church Workers in colleges and universities; Association of Colleges; Minutes of the Executive Committee and corresp., 1934 (Box 11, Folder 143)
    - Twenty-fourth Annual Meeting CCBE - Atlanta, GA, Jan 16, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 144)
    - Twenty-fifth Annual Meeting CCBE, New York City, Jan 15, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 145)
    - Twenty-sixth Annual Meeting CCBE, Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C., Jan 11-15, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 146)
    - Twenty-seventh Annual Meeting CCBE, Chicago, Ill., Jan 19, 1938 (Box 12, Folder 147)
    - Twenty-eighth Annual Meeting CCBE, Brown Hotel, Louisville, KY, Jan 9-13, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 148)
    - Twenty-ninth Annual Meeting CCBE Philadelphia program and corresp., Jan 10, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 149)
    - Thirtieth Annual Meeting Callifornia - both CCBE and National Conference of Church-Related Colleges, Jan 8, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 150)
    - Thirty-first Annual Meeting, Baltimore, Maryland. The 1942 annual meetings were booked for Hotel Cleveland, Cleveland, Ohio, but were transferred to Baltimore because of call of college parents to Baltimore to a meeting due to the war situation., Jan 5, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 151)
    - Thirty-second Annual Meeting - CCBE and NCCRC Meetings Jan 13 planned for Hotel Cleveland, Cleveland, OH but not held because of travel conditions due to war., Jan 10-15, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 152)
    - Thirty-third Annual Meeting CCBE, Cincinnati, Ohio, The Netherland Plaza, Jan 12, 1944 (Box 12, Folder 153)
    - Thirty-fourth Annual Meeting CCBE, Hotel Claridya, Atlantic City, NJ, Jan 10, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 154)
    - Thirty-fifth Annual Meeting CCBE, Cleveland, Jan 7-11, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 155)
    - Thirty-sixth Annual Meeting CCBE Boston, Jan 13-17, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 156)
    - Thirty-seventh Annual Meeting CCBE, 1948 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - Other Conferences
    - First Interchurch Student Conference Naperville, Ill., Dec 27-31, 1938 (Box 13, Folder 158)
    - Second Interchurch Student Conference Naperville, Ill., Dec 27-31, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 159)
    - Miscellaneous Student Conferences: Amsterdam Conference List of delegates, July 1939 (Box 13, Folder 160)
    - Misc. Student Conferences, 1936-1945 (Box 13, Folder 161)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews pamphlets, lectures, and corresp., 1939-1945 (Box 13, Folder 162)
    - National Laymen's Conference program of meeting, questions, and corresp., 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 163)
    - Pastor's Institute and Education Conference program, Summer 1942 (Box 13, Folder 164)
    - Peace International: Minutes of meeting of the program information exchange, 1945 (Box 13, Folder 165)
    - Programs - Educational Conferences suggestions, 1936-1940 (Box 13, Folder 166)
    - Triennial Conference of Church Workers in Universities and Colleges of the United States, December 29-31, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - Triennial Conference Church Workers with Students. File #2 - Program brochures and corresp., 1940 (Box 13, Folder 168)
- Organizations, Series IV
  - Committee on United Christian Youth Movement minutes and corresp., 1937 (Box 14, Folder 169)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation pamphlets, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 170)
  - Miscellaneous promotional materials from colleges, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - Miscellaneous promotional materials from colleges continued, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 172)
  - Mormon Board of Education quotes, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 173)
  - Organizational Programs of Denominations; Congregational-Christian- filed within May, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 174)
  - Secondary Schools Standards report, 1935 (Box 14, Folder 175)
  - United Nations - charter and later developments, pamphlets, articles, UNESCO docs, reports, etc, 1945 (Box 14, Folder 176)
  - United Student Peace Committee, 1939-1940 (Box 14, Folder 177)
  - Universal Christian Council - meeting file, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 178)
  - Works Project Admin. Survey Form, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 179)
  - World Conference of Faith and Order; minutes of joint meeting, 1939-1940 (Box 14, Folder 180)
  - World Council of Churches meeting report, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 181)
  - World Federation of Education Associations pamphlet, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 182)